Curriculum Vitae

Name: Patrick Kawaye Chimseu

Email:pchimseu@luanar.ac.mw/ pkkchimseu@gmail.com

ORCID: 0009-0008-4049-7505

Contact Address: CARD LUANAR, P.O. Box 219, Lilongwe,

Malawi Nationality: Malawian Mobile number: + 265 888 11 99 47

Personal Profile

I am an innovative and pro-active Economist with vast experience in research, innovation and development work. I have a Masters in Agricultural and Applied Economics under the Collaborative Master of Science in Agricultural and Applied Economics in Africa (CMAAE) from LUANAR and University of Pretoria, a BSc. In Agribusiness Management, and I also hold Postgraduate Certificates in Behavioral Economics and Property Rights, Tenure Reform Markets & Social welfare from NMBU and LUANAR. I have vast experience in conducting training, research, and diverse skills in data management and analysis using Python, R programming, Stata, Google Colab, Excel, Survey solution, Mwater, Kobo collect, NVivo, and ATLAS.ti among others. I have been involved in different research studies by different research institutions including MUST, NCST, MSU, NMBU, Purdue University, FAO, and IFPRI among others. I participated in policy programing on Development of Model Cluster in Malawi, Drafting of MSMES Bill and I have also done University consultancy work for public and private companies. I hold certificate in Scientific Writing; Policy Brief writing, Project Management and in Business Incubation and Innovation. My current research interest is on application of Structural Equation Models (Latent Class Model), AI and behavioral experiments in rural development.

Selected Research, Innovation and Consultancy work

2024 Purdue University-MUST - Establishing Farmer Resilience Thresholds Linked to Climate Insurance Coverage

2024 MUST- Development of MUST branded, research based products

2024 LUANAR- Trust and Gender-Based Consumption Decisions for Bio-fortified Staple Foods in Malawi

2023 UNESCO -TWAS- LUANAR- Development Carbs Exchange Malawi

2023 MUST- Data Management and Analysis for THES project

2023 MUST -Designing and Development of Secondary School STEM Portal

2023 MUST - Designing and Development of Websites and Content Management System

2023 USAID-LUANAR- Nutrition 4 Health – Development of Malawi Food Data System (MAFOODS)

2023 MUST- Setting up and Configuring AWS Servers and World Bank Survey Solution Software 2022

LUANAR- Development of Digital Fish Marketing Platform in Malawi.

2023 MUST- NBM Training Needs Assessment

2023 Ministry of Trade - Policy Programing on Development of Model Cluster in Malawi

2023 Ultra-Processed Foods: Nova Classification in Malawi

2023 Malnutrition in older adults at hospital admission in Malawi study

2023 Dietary Quality, Food, and Nutrition Security Among Adults with Pre-diabetes in Malawi study 2022

Data Management for Smallholder vegetable farming systems for enhancing food security and income in Malawi household study

2022 Commodity Climate Risk Assessment for TRADE

2021 Data management for NMBU-LUANAR SMARTEX Projects

2021 "The missing link of women in higher education in Malawi: the lack of representation of women In Science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) and sanitation education".

2016 Data Management for USAID project called (Integrating Nutrition in Value Chains.)

Education History

2023: MSc. In Agricultural and Applied Economics Institution: LUANAR & University of Pretoria

2023: Postgraduate Certificate in Behavioral Economics Institution: NMBU & LUANAR

2023: Postgraduate Certificate in Property Rights, Tenure Reform Markets & Social welfare **Institution:** NMBU & LUANAR

2013-2017: BSc. In Agribusiness Management Institution: Bunda College of Agriculture, LUANAR.

2011-2012: Malawi School Certificate of Education (12pts) Institution: Mulunguzi Secondary School

2009-2010: Junior Certificate of Education

Other Awards

Certificate in Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Human Subject Protections (Perdue

University)

Certificate in AI in Higher Education An Overview (Perdue University)

Certificate in AI in Higher Education An Overview (Perdue University)

Certificate in Scientific Writing (Kansans State University and LUANAR)

Certificate in Project Management (GIZ).

Certificate in business innovation (African Agribusiness Incubation Network)

National Commission for Science and Technology Small Grant

Outstanding student; best student in Mathematics, Computer and Agriculture

Employment History

June 2024 - Now: Research Fellow, LUANAR Center for Agricultural Research and Development

June 2023 – June 2024: Project Officer & Research Fellow, Malawi University of Science and Technology

November 2020 to May 2023: Intern at LUANAR (Directorate of Research and Agribusiness Department)

December, 2018 - November 2020: Agribusiness Lecture at Mwimba College of Agriculture

November 2017 - November, 2018: Marketing and Trade Officer at Farm Concern International

Core Competencies

- a. Excellent skills using different research tools (Google Colab, R programming, Python, Stata, NVivo, Atlas t.i, Excel, Survey Solution, Mwater, Kobo collect).
- b. Excellent skill in Data analysis, M&E, Machine learning modeling, Kotlin and Flutter Apps development and Agile software development
- c. Excellent analytical skills and good in writing and data management
- d. In-depth knowledge in conducting research
- e. Software designing and development
- f. Drafting Memorandum of Understanding (MOU)
- g. Excellent skills in conducting training, developing manuals, and writing reports, and designing graphics using Adobe software
- h. Excellent communication or interpersonal skills; English & Chichewa

- i. Team building skills; quick learner; Ability to work with minimum supervision.
- j. Good Microsoft Office skills (Excel, Word, Excel, Power point, Projects and Publisher).

AREAS OF INTEREST

Research and development, Developing Digital M&E systems and Software, Data analysis, Machine learning, Marketing and Behavioral Experiments.

PERSONALITY

Honest, Innovative, Royal, Hardworking and Friendly

REFEREES

Director of Research and Outreach Associate Prof. Samson Katengeza LUANAR, Bunda College P.O.Box 219 Lilongwe. skatengeza@luanar.ac.mw

Mobile: +265 995 44 62 02

Prof. Emmanuel Kaunda LUANAR, Bunda College P.O.Box 219 Lilongwe. ekaunda@luanar.ac.mw Mobile: +265 999 51 07 96

Mobile: +265 999 55 24 00

Director of MUST Institute of Industrial Research and Innovation Prof. David Mkwambisi MUST P.O. Box 5196 Limbe dmkwambisi@must.ac.mw